Finding Aid for Muschenheim, William. Architectural drawings and papers. 1925-1990
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Project Files
  - Job 54, Mr. F.B. Kirkbride
    - Franklin B. Kirkbride cottage, (New Canaan, Conn.)
      - Drawings, #.01150-.01198 1938-1940, 1946, 49 sheets: various media; or smaller 76.5 x 95 cm.; 30-1/8 x 37-3/8 inches
        - [Oxford Deluxe cabinets Kitchen installation, showing plan and interior elevations with measurements] / Bradley Kitchen Cabinet Co.; drawn by M.R. 05/20/1938 [revised], 5/24/1938, NYDA.1986.004.01195
        - [Duplicate copy of 1986.004.01195], NYDA.1986.004.01196
        - Proposed Kitchen cabinets [showing plans and interior elevations, with measurements]: No. 1134/ Steeline Kitchen Co., 5/20/1938, NYDA.1986.004.01197
          (Verso shows notes regarding cabinets.)
        - Proposed Kitchen cabinets [showing plans and interior elevations, with measurements] / submitted by the Art Metal Kitchens June 3, 1938, NYDA.1986.004.01198
      - Papers
        - notes, brochures, color sample, and misc. material. (Box A7, Folder 54-4)
        - archival: specifications. (Box A7, Folder 54-5)
        - archival: certificates, orders, statements. (Box A7, Folder 54-6)
          (Worked with: Arundell Clarke; Kurt Versen Company (lighting); Modern Metal Mfg. Co.; Thonet Brothers; Medason Inc.; and others.)
        - archival: correspondence, pamphlets, business cards, notes. (Box A7, Folder 54-7)
          (Correspondents include: Franklin B. Kirkbride; Five Wells; Modern Metal Manufacturing Co.; Medason Co.; The Formica Insulation Co.; Adams-Faber Company (building construction); Art Metal Kitchens; Excel Metal Cabinet Company, Inc.; Frank D. Rich Co. (builders); Jenkins manufacturing Company; Kurt Versen (lighting); and others.)
  - Job 55, Architectural League
    - [Architectural League Exhibit 1938]
      - Drawings, #.01199-.01206 December 1937-January 1938, 8 sheets: various media; or smaller 44.7 x 60.5 cm.; 17-5/8 x 23-7/8 inches
        This set consists of 3 blueprints on paper, 2 pencil on tracing paper, 2 pencil with pastel on tracing paper, 1 pencil with pastel and paint on tracing paper, and 1 pencil on paper
        - [Music room]: isometric [i.e. axonometric view] and elevs. of sofa and corner cabinet: Drawing Study #2, 1/14/1938, NYDA.1986.004.01199
        - 1/4" scale plan and elevs. of music rm. showing position of sofa, corner cabinet and bench: Drawing Study #3, 1/21/1938, NYDA.1986.004.01200
        - 1/4" scale plan and elevs. of music rm. showing position of sofa, corner cabinet and bench: Drawing Study #3 1/21/1938, NYDA.1986.004.01201 R; Blueprint on paper.
          (Copied from 1986.004.01200.)
        - [Sketch of plan(?) and elevation(?)]., NYDA.1986.004.01201 V
          (Possibly for the Arts and Crafts exhibit.)
        - [Duplicate copy of 1986.004.01201R]., NYDA.1986.004.01202
        - Arts and Crafts Exhibit: plan and elevs. of tentative lay-out: Drawing Study #4, 1/26/1938, NYDA.1986.004.01203
        - Music room for the Architectural League Exhibit 1938 [showing plan and elevation] / Voorhees Gmelin & Walker;, 1/17/1938, NYDA.1986.004.01204
          (Architects' names have been crossed out with a pen and an illegible name written above it.)
        - Preliminary sketch of twin sofa and capehart combination [showing an axonometric view] 12/29/1937, NYDA.1986.004.01205
        - [Sketch of corner(?) showing a plan]., NYDA.1986.004.01206
      - Papers
        - archival (Box A7, Folder 55-2)
          (found with drawing Folder 4, 1 sheet: 1 small page of notes.)
        - pamphlet, brochure, small page of notes. (Box A7, Folder 55-3)
        - archival: correspondence, exhibition agreement, and other misc. material. (Box A7, Folder 55-6)
          (Corresponded with Hugh Ferriss (re exhibition of WMIs work at The Architectural League), and others.)
  - Job 56, Wheaton College
    - [Wheaton College Competition (Norton, Mass.). Art Center]
      - Drawings, #.01207-.01279 1938, 73 sheets: various media; or smaller 60.8 x 97.5 cm.; 24 x 38-3/8 inches
        This set consists of 65 pencil on tracing paper, 1 pencil with pastel on tracing paper, 4 pencil on paper and 3 stats on paper. All drawings were originally found filed in File no. 55, folder 4. 1986.004.01275-.01279 were originally located with a letter to Muschenheim from L.E. Helbig, manager of Snead & Company, dated March 23, 1938. Competition winner was Richard M. Bennett and Caleb Hornbostel of New York--from letter to Muschenheim from George Nelson of Architectural Forum, New York, dated June 13, 1938
        - [Diagram of presentation board showing placement of block plans and notation]., NYDA.1986.004.01207
        - [Diagram of presentation board showing placement of site plan and elevations]., NYDA.1986.004.01208
        - [Exterior perspective study, showing main entrance]., NYDA.1986.004.01209
        - [Study of an axonometric view showing auditorium rounded on roof]., NYDA.1986.004.01210
        - [Study of an axonometric view]., NYDA.1986.004.01211
        - [Study of an axonometric view showing windows]., NYDA.1986.004.01212
        - [Study of an axonometric view showing windows and patios]., NYDA.1986.004.01213
        - [Study of an axonometric view showing lines of study]., NYDA.1986.004.01214
        - [Study of an axomometric view showing site]., NYDA.1986.004.01215
        - [Study of an axomometric view of site]., NYDA.1986.004.01216
        - [Study of an axonometric view of site with areas keyed with letters]., NYDA.1986.004.01217
        - [Study of a bird's-eye axonometric view]., NYDA.1986.004.01218
        - [Study of a bird's-eye axonometric view showing site]., NYDA.1986.004.01219
        - Plot plan., NYDA.1986.004.01271
        - Plot plan., NYDA.1986.004.01272
          (Reduced stat of 1986.004.01271.)
        - Plot plan [showing grading]., NYDA.1986.004.01220
        - [Study of site plan with grading]., NYDA.1986.004.01221
        - [Study of a block plan keyed with letters]., NYDA.1986.004.01274
          (Key chart is in archives for this project and refers to cubic feet.)
        - [Study of a site plan with areas keyed with letters]., NYDA.1986.004.01222
        - [Study of a block plan]., NYDA.1986.004.01223
        - [Study showing block plan]., NYDA.1986.004.01224
        - [Sketch of block plan]., NYDA.1986.004.01225
        - [Studies of elevations and axonometric view]., NYDA.1986.004.01226
        - [Study of elevation of front(?)]., NYDA.1986.004.01227
        - [Sketch of elevation of front(?)]., NYDA.1986.004.01228
        - [Study of elevation of side(?)]., NYDA.1986.004.01229
        - [Sketch of elevation of side(?)]., NYDA.1986.004.01230
        - [Study of exterior elevation of rear(?)]., N YDA.1986.004.01231
        - [Study of partial elevation of rear(?)]., NYDA.1986.004.01232
        - [Sketch of partial exterior elevation of rear(?)]., NYDA.1986.004.01233
        - [Sketch of partial elevation of rear(?)]., NYDA.1986.004.01234
        - [Sketch of partial elevation showing rear(?)]., NYDA.1986.004.01235
        - [Study of exterior elevation of side(?)]., NYDA.1986.004.01236
        - [Sketch of partial exterior elevation of side(?)]., NYDA.1986.004.01237
        - First floor, second floor [and a longitudinal section of main auditorium and adjacent areas]., NYDA.1986.004.01273
        - [Sketch of main auditorium showing floor plan with seating and adjacent areas]., NYDA.1986.004.01238
        - [Study of main auditorium and adjacent areas, showing floor plan]., NYDA.1986.004.01263
        - [Sketch of main auditorium showing floor plan with seating and adjacent areas]., NYDA.1986.004.01239
        - [Sketch of main auditorium showing floor plan and part of library]., NYDA.1986.004.01240
        - [Sketch of main auditorium showing floor plan with seating]., NYDA.1986.004.01241
        - [Sketch of main auditorium showing floor plan with some side rooms]., NYDA.1986.004.01242
        - [Sketch of main auditorium showing floor plan]., NYDA.1986.004.01243
        - Balcony level of library [showing floor plan]., NYDA.1986.004.01244
        - [Study of balcony level of library showing floor plan with shelving, railing, and another balcony(?)]., NYDA.1986.004.01245
        - [Study of balcony level of library showing floor plan with some shelving]., NYDA.1986.004.01246
        - Alcoves in a school library [showing sketches of a partial plan and an elevation of] setting out of rolling book stacks in steel., NYDA.1986.004.01275
        - [Sketches of elevations of vertical box-file stack and of horizontal box-file stack for music with notes and measurements]., NYDA.1986.004.01276
        - Special study rooms [showing sketches of plans]., NYDA.1986.004.01277
        - Reference rms. [showing sketches of a plan with layout of table and chairs, and a section of a table with a reading lamp, with notes and measurements]., NYDA.1986.004.01278
        - [Sketch showing plan of library reading table with chairs, including measurements]., NYDA.1986.004.01279
        - [Study for small auditorium and adjacent studios, classrooms and coatroom showing floor plan]., NYDA.1986.004.01247
        - [Sketches of coat room and small offices(?) adjacent to small auditorium showing floor plans]., NYDA.1986.004.01248
        - [Study of small auditorium, adjacent classrooms, and a coatroom with a rounded corner showing floor plan]., NYDA.1986.004.01249
        - [Sketch of small auditorium, adjacent classrooms, and a coatroom with a rounded corner showing a floor plan and computations for space]., NYDA.1986.004.01250
        - [Sketch of small auditorium and adjacent rooms showing a floor plan and computations for space]., NYDA.1986.004.01251
        - [Sketch of small auditorium and adjacent classrooms, studios and coat racks(?) showing floor plan and detail floor plans]., NYDA.1986.004.01252
        - [Sketch of small auditorium and adjacent classrooms, studios and coat rack(?) showing floor plan]., NYDA.1986.004.01253
        - [Sketches of small auditorium and adjacent classrooms, studios and coat racks(?) showing floor plan and detail plans]., NYDA.1986.004.01254
        - [Study of small auditorium and adjacent classrooms, studios and coatroom showing 2 floor plans]., NYDA.1986.004.01255
        - [Sketch of small auditorium and adjacent classrooms, studios and coatroom showing 2 floor plans]., NYDA.1986.004.01256
        - CODEN [Sketch of small auditorium and adjacent classrooms, studios, and coatroom showing floor plan and a detail plan]., NYDA.1986.004.01257
        - [Study of 2 floor plans showing a hall with classrooms and a hall with practice rooms(?) and a lecture hall]., NYDA.1986.004.01258
        - [Sketch of 2 floor plans showing a hall with classrooms and a hall with practice rooms(?) and a lecture hall]., NYDA.1986.004.01259
        - [Study of a hall and classrooms showing a plan]., NYDA.1986.004.01260
        - [Study of a hall, practice rooms(?) and a lecture hall showing a plan]., NYDA.1986.004.01261
        - [Sketch of a hall, practice rooms(?) and a lecture hall showing a plan]. Drawing notes cubic feet and is labeled "Music"., NYDA.1986.004.01262
        - [Study of unidentified area with one set of stairs, showing floor plan]., NYDA.1986.004.01264
        - [Study of unidentified area with two sets of stairs, showing floor plan]., NYDA.1986.004.01265
        - [Study of an auditorium showing plan and longitudinal section]., NYDA.1986.004.01266
        - [Study of unidentified area showing a longitudinal section]., NYDA.1986.004.01267
        - [Study of an auditorium(?) showing a longitudinal section]., NYDA.1986.004.01268
        - [Unidentified sketch showing stairs]., NYDA.1986.004.01269
        - [Unidentified sketch]., NYDA.1986.004.01270
      - Papers
        - archival: correspondence, photographs, notes, clippings. (Box A7, Folder 56-1)
          (13 2x2, B&W photographs of [proposed site for art center., Approx. 16 items of material related to a competition to select an architect for proposed art center at Wheaton College.)
      - Photographs (Box B10)
  - Job 57, Random House
    - [Book jacket design for "Murder at the New York World's Fair"]
      - Drawings, #.01280-.01287 circa 1938, 8 sheets: various media; or smaller 37.7 x 46.5 cm.; 14-7/8 x 18-3/8 inches
        This set consists of 4 pencil on tracing paper, 2 stats, 1 blueprint on paper, and 1 watercolor on tracing paper. "Murder at the World's Fair" was written by Freeman Dana
        - [Book jack design showing front cover and spine]., NYDA.1986.004.01280; Watercolor on tracing paper; 32 x 29.4 cm. (12-5/8 x 11-5/8 in.)
        - [Study for front cover design]., NYDA.1986.004.01281
        - [Study for front cover design]., NYDA.1986.004.01282; Stat on paper.
          (Enlarged copy of 1986.004.01281.)
        - [Study of the trylon and perisphere]., NYDA.1986.004.01283
        - [Study of the trylon and perisphere]., NYDA.1986.004.01284; Stat on paper.
          (Reduced and shaded copy of 1986.004.01283.)
        - [Study of front cover design showing trylon and perisphere on the right with lettering below]., NYDA.1986.004.01285
        - [Study of front cover design showing some lettering]., NYDA.1986.004.01286
        - [Study of front cover and spine design showing trylon and perisphere with lettering at the top]., NYDA.1986.004.01287
      - Papers
        - archival (Box A7, Folder 57-3)
          (1 sheet found w/ drawing Folder 1: 1 bill for services rendered in connection with book jacket design "Murder at the New York World's Fair.")
  - Job 58, Mrs. Malcolm D. Whitman
    - Mrs. M.D. Whitman apartment, 320 Park Ave., Alterations
      - Drawings, #.01288-.01301, 14 sheets: various media; or smaller 43 x 83.8 cm.; 17 x 33 inches
        This set consists of 13 pencil on paper and 1 pencil with pastel on tracing paper
        - Ceil. plan, elevs. and details [showing ceiling plan of living room, elevs. and section of mantel in liv. rm., interior elevations of north and west windows of dng. rm., and a detail section, all with notes and measurements]: Drawing 1-A, 11/2/38, revised 11/9/1938, NYDA.1986.004.01288
        - [Sketch of living room showing plan with measurements], NYDA.1986.004.01289
        - [Sketch of unidentified room showing a plan with measurements and notes], NYDA.1986.004.01290
        - [Sketch of unidentified plan with measurements], NYDA.1986.004.01291
        - [Sketch of an unidentified interior elevation and detail with measurements]. Notes information on a railing, NYDA.1986.004.01292
        - [Sketch of an unidentified interior elevation with notes and measurements], NYDA.1986.004.01293
        - [Sketch of a wall with a window showing an interior elevation with measurements], NYDA.1986.004.01294
        - [Sketch of a wall with a cabinet(?) underneath, showing an interior elevation with measurements], NYDA.1986.004.01295
        - [Sketch of a wall with two windows with a cabinet(?) below, showing an interior elevation with measurements], NYDA.1986.004.01296
        - [Sketch of an unidentified item with measurements], NYDA.1986.004.01297
        - [Sketch of mantel showing an elevation with measurements], NYDA.1986.004.01298
        - [Sketch of a cabinet with sliding doors showing an oblique view with measurements], NYDA.1986.004.01299
        - [Sketch of an unidentified object showing an elevation with measurements], NYDA.1986.004.01300
        - [Sketch of 2 iron gates for windows], NYDA.1986.004.01301
      - Papers
        - archival: correspondence, notes, statements, estimates, brochures, orders, receipts, specifications. (Box A7, Folder 58-5)
          (Worked with: Kurt Versen Company (lighting); H. Carmichael Smith (carpets); Clark & Howes (upholstered furniture); Medason Inc. (furniture); Standard Air conditioning Inc.; The George S. Nichols Company (electrical engineers); Kitchen Maid Sales Company; Beaux Arts Lighting Co.; Raustein & Festis (painting, decorating); Thonet Brothers (furniture); and others.)
        - archival: orders, certificates, bills, statements, and other accounts information. (Box A7, Folder 58-6)
          (Worked with: The George S. Nichols Company (electrical engineers); Beaux Arts Lighting Co., Inc.; Modern Metal Manufacturing Co.; Gustav F. Wild (glass & mirrors); Bronx Window Shade & Awning Co., Inc.; The United States Bronze Sign Co., Inc.; H. Carmichael Smith (carpets); Lustbader Upholstery Co.; Raustin & Festis (painting, decorating); Reliance Sign Company; The Gould-Mersereau Co., Inc. (drapery, carpet and cabinet hardware); Kurt Versen Company (lighting); Thonet Brothers (furniture); Otto Kirschner (carpentry); Joseph Muench (carpentry); Frederic Blank & Co. (wall paper); and others.)
    - Countess Mara's Shop, 338 Park Ave., NYC
      - Drawings, #.01302-.01319 1938, 1941, 18 sheets: various media; or smaller 76 x 114.2 cm.; 30 x 45 inches
        This set consists of 9 pencil on tracing paper, 4 pencil with pastel on tracing paper, 3 blueline prints on paper and 2 blueprints on paper
        - Floor plan and details [with elevation of plywood railing looking east and a section thru recessed ceil. fixtures, with notes]: Drawing 1 10/12/1938, NYDA.1986.004.01302
        - Elevations [showing south, west, north, and east interiors and the Park Avenue exterior, and a section thru the show window]: Drawing 2, 10/2/1938, NYDA.1986.004.01303
        - [Elevations on south, west, north, and east interiors]. Blueprint, NYDA.1986.004.01304
          (. Copied from 1986.004.01303.)
        - Flexglass wall [showing an elevation of west wall showing areas which are to receive flexglass]: Drawing 2A 8/25/1941, NYDA.1986.004.01305
        - F.S.Details and elev. of int. south window frames [with notes and measurements]: Drawing 3, 10/9/1938, NYDA.1986.004.01306
        - Glass panels for back of show-windows [showing an isometric view]: Drawing 4, 11/7/1938, NYDA.1986.004.01307
        - Lettering on entrance door [showing an elevation of the door with notes and measurements]: Drawing 5 11/10/1938, NYDA.1986.004.01308
        - [Study of elevation of entrance door], NYDA.1986.004.01312
        - [Sketch of elevation of entrance door], NYDA.1986.004.01313
        - Table [showing an] isometric [i.e. axonometric] drawing [with notes and measurements]: Drawing 6 11/21/1938, NYDA.1986.004.01309
        - Leather-covered couch (isometric) [i.e. axonometric view]: Drawing 6-B 8/6/1941, NYDA.1986.004.01310
        - Aluminum strips at radiator enclosures [showing elevation with notes and measurements]: Drawing 7, 12/1/1938, NYDA.1986.004.01311
        - [Study of] design of bronze lettering [for store facade showing exterior elevation] 10/18/1938, NYDA.1986.004.01314
        - [Sketches of unidentified objects with measurements], NYDA.1986.004.01315
        - Reflector details [showing F.S. cross sections and longitudinal sections with notes and measurements]: Drawing no. 3810-24 / Beaux Arts Lighting Co. Inc.; drawn by A.E. Philipps 10/24/1938, NYDA.1986.004.01316
        - Fluorescent window refl. [to illuminate show windows showing F.S. cross section and inside elevation]: Drawing no. 3812-2A / Beaux Arts Lighting Co. Inc.; drawn by A.E. Philipps, 12/2/1938, NYDA.1986.004.01317
        - Window refl. details [of show window spot light showing a F.S. cross section and an elevation with notes and measurements]: Drawing no. 3812-15 / Beaux Arts Lighting Co. Inc.; drawn by A.E. Philipps 12/15/1938, NYDA.1986.004.01318
        - Type "L" lumiline trough [showing sections with notes and measurements]: Drawing no. 48-193 / Kurt Versen, Inc.; drawn by W.R. 8/19/1941, NYDA.1986.004.01319
      - Papers
        - Countess Mara: (Box A7, Folder 58-4)
          (9 samples of various materials, 3 pages of notes, 3 photostats of crown drawing.)
  - Job 59, Baroness Hilla von Rebay
    - Baroness Hilla von Rebay barn, Westport, CT
      - Drawings, #.01320-.01338 October 1938-January 1939, 19 sheets: various media; or smaller 80 x 111.7 cm.; 31-1/2 x 44 inches
        This set consists of 9 pencil with pastel on tracing paper, 5 pencil on tracing paper, 4 pencil on paper, and 1 blueline print on paper
        - Plan and sections and det'ls [with notes and measurements]: Drawing 1 10/26/1938 revised 11/2/38, 11/28/1938, NYDA.1986.004.01320
        - Int. and ext. elevations [and a F.S.D., with notes and measurements]: Drawing 2 10/26/1938 revised 11/2/38, 11/28/1938, NYDA.1986.004.01321
        - Panelling on walls and ceil. [showing reflected ceiling plan, interior elevations, and a F.S.D., with notes]: Drawing 3 11/30/1938, NYDA.1986.004.01322
        - F.S.D. of fl. and base [with notes]: Drawing 3A, 12/1/1938, NYDA.1986.004.01323
        - 3" scale details, except as otherwise noted [showing elevation of ladder, details of removable panels, section of a plywood apron, and details of a door, with notes and measurements]: Drawing 4, 12/5/1938, NYDA.1986.004.01324
        - Elev. [from the side] and plan of ladder [with a F.S.D. plan of tread]: Drawing 4A 1/23/1939, NYDA.1986.004.01325
        - Elev. [from the side] and plan of ladder [with notes]: Drawing 4B 1/25/1939, NYDA.1986.004.01326
        - Alt. to ice-house adj. barn: plan, sects. elevs. and details, [with notes]: Drawing 5, 12/9/1938, NYDA.1986.004.01327
        - Alternate plan for dressing rm. [with elev. of north wall and sect. showing east wall of new closet, with notes]: Drawing 6 12/26/1938, NYDA.1986.004.01328
        - Plans [of ceiling and closet] and elevs. of bedrm. in loft space and 3" scale details [of windows and panels, with notes and measurements]: Drawing 7 1/6/1939, NYDA.1986.004.01329
        - Isometric [i.e. axonometric] Drawing of book-cases in N.W. corner of studio [with notes and measurements]: Drawing 8 1/25/1939, NYDA.1986.004.01330
        - [Sketch of elevation of exterior side view], NYDA.1986.004.01331
        - [Sketch of elevation of front exterior and a detail of a window(?) with measurements], NYDA.1986.004.01332
        - [Sketch of foundation(?) plan, with measurements], NYDA.1986.004.01333
        - [Sketch of foundation(?) plan showing pipe lay-out, with measurements], NYDA.1986.004.01334
        - [Sketch of section from the front, with measurements], NYDA.1986.004.01335
        - [Sketch of section(?), noted with computations], NYDA.1986.004.01336
        - Picture gallery reflector details [showing F.S. cross section, a front elevation and a reflected plan, with notes and measurements]: Drawing no. 3812-2 / Beaux Arts Lighting co. Inc.; drawn by A.S. Philipps, 12-2-38., NYDA.1986.004.01337
          (Drawing was originally located with a letter to Muschenheim, from A.E. Philipps of Beaux Arts Lighting Co. Inc., dated 12/2/1938 The letter is located in Archival Folder 3.)
        - [Sketch of section of spotlight, with notes and measurements], NYDA.1986.004.01338
      - Papers
        - 5 pages of notes. (Box A7, Folder 59-2)
        - 5 pages of notes, 2 pages product information, 1 railroad schedule. (Box A7, Folder 59-3)
        - prints: photographs showing interior and exterior views, 4 items (Box A7, Folder 59-4)
          (Folder 11)
        - archival: (Box A7, Folder 59-5)
          (specifications, schedules, proposal, bulletin, product information for Standard Plumbing Fixtures.)
        - archival: (Box A8, Folder 59-6)
          (bills, cash allowance forms, agreements, orders, certificates.)
        - archival: correspondence, notes, agreement. (Box A8, Folder 59-7)
          (Worked with: Beaux Arts Lighting Co., Inc.; Miller-Reed, Inc. (builders & general contractors); P. & F. Corbin (locks & builders' hardware); and others. Also corresponded with Baroness Hilla von Rebay.)
  - Job 60, The Solomon R. Guggenheim Foundation
    - Solomon R. Guggenheim Foundation